<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An excellent tretise, shevving suche perillous, and contagious infirmities, as shall insue. 1559. and .1566 vvith the signes, causes, accidentes, and curatio, for the health of such as inhabit the. 7.8. and. 9. climat. compiled by Maister Michael Nostrodamus, Doctor in Phisicke, and translated into Englysh at the desire of Laurentius Philotus, Tyl.</title>
            <author>Nostradamus, 1503-1566.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1559</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120211</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855410</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855410</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20903</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1110:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An excellent tretise, shevving suche perillous, and contagious infirmities, as shall insue. 1559. and .1566 vvith the signes, causes, accidentes, and curatio, for the health of such as inhabit the. 7.8. and. 9. climat. compiled by Maister Michael Nostrodamus, Doctor in Phisicke, and translated into Englysh at the desire of Laurentius Philotus, Tyl.</title>
                  <author>Nostradamus, 1503-1566.</author>
                  <author>Philotus, Laurentius.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Day, dwelling ouer Aldersgate beneath S. Martins.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1559]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An excellent Tretiſe, ſhevving ſuche perillous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious infirmities, as ſhall inſue .1569. and .1566. vvith the ſignes, cauſes, acci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dentes, and curatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the health of ſuch as inhabit the .7. 8. and .9. climat. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by Maiſter Michael Noſtroda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Doctor in Phiſicke, and tranſlated into Englyſh at the deſire of Laurentius Philotus, Tyl.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶Imprinted at London by Ihon Day, dwelling ouer Alderſgate beneath S. Martins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:2"/>
            <head>The Contentes of this Tretiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Epiſtle.</item>
               <item>A Regiment for vvynter.</item>
               <item>A Regiment for the Spring.</item>
               <item>A Regiment for Sommer.</item>
               <item>A Regiment for Autumne.</item>
               <item>Of the Peſtilence.</item>
               <item>Of the bluddy flix.</item>
               <item>Of the burning feuer.</item>
               <item>Of the quartayne.</item>
               <item>Of the quotidian ague.</item>
               <item>Of the catarrhus or revvme.</item>
               <item>Of the plureſies.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:2"/>
            <head>To the right excellent, noble, &amp; vertuous Lord, my Lord Emanieu, Byſhoppe of Macon, Pronotharie of the Apoſtolique Seat, etc Michel Noſtrodamus, your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and obedient ſeruaunt, &amp; oratour, vviſheth health &amp; long life in Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued youre let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (ryght reve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rende &amp; my ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry good Lord) the .xxvi. daye of May .1558. in vvhich, you declare your a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bondau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not only to me, in takyng my trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of my Prognoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Almanack vvhiche I ſent you, in the beſt parte: but alſo to all men, vvhan you vvyſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cum forth as a vvarning to corect and
<pb facs="tcp:20903:3"/>
amende their ill lyfe, and diſſembling trade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vvhere as your excellency af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmith, that thinges forſeen may be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, or at the leeſt the malice of them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigatid, and that the ſicknes and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this yeare folovvyng, be diuers in their kynde, dangerous, mortal, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally reigning: for vvhiche men ſhall ſcant haue time to counſell vvith the ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd doctors, and maiſters of Phiſicke. VVherfore to ſhovv my dutie, and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruice vnto you at this tyme, I haue at youre requeſte, deuiſed a treatyſe, in vvhiche I haue touched the diſeaſes, and maladies, vvhiche ſhall ſpring the yeare of .1559. and .1560. vvith the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation from them: and the curyng ſuch as ſhalbe troubled vvith any of them. And if I ſhall deſerue any prayſe, and laude of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people for my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I vvill they giue all that to youre honour, vvhiche are the only occaſion of this enterpriſe. And if there ſhall any fault be founde in this booke, let them
<pb facs="tcp:20903:3"/>
aſcribe that to the difficultie of the vvorke, and not to my negligence. Thus I leue to trouble your Lordſhyppe any longer, vvilling ſuche as vvill take pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by my labour, to haue my medicines vvell made by the helpe of good and ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyd Apothecaries. And ſuche as may haue the lernyd doctours and maiſters of Phyſick, I vvyſhe that they leue my booke, and folovv their counſel, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng anye expence: For lyfe is more of value, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mony, or treaſure. (For I make my boke for ther cauſe vvhiche can not haue the lernyd vvith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.) God ſende your excellency, long life, bodely helth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of honor.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Salo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the prouince of Craux, <date>the .xii. of Auguſt. 1558.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="regimen">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:4"/>
            <head>A Regiment for the VVynter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE I finde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitucion of the aire (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the .xii. of December .1558. vntil the .xi. daye of March ſo lovving .1559) to bring forth mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che colde, rayning vveather, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiall and ſtinking myſtes, by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Saturne in the Eaſt, as I haue ſaide in my Prognoſtication: cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Flegmatick humors to abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of vvhiche ſhall ſpring Catarrhus, Reumes, Head ache, Peſtilentiall ſicknes, and Sciatica, vvith Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghinges,
<pb facs="tcp:20903:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſuche like, ſo that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall die therof, as vvell yonge as olde. Mors etiam ſaxis, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moribuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> venit. In ſo muche that fevve ſhalbe free from this calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vvherfore to keepe the body in health it ſhalbe expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to eſchevv bathinge, ſluggiſhnes, long ſleepe, vſing euer before meate ſome kinde of exerciſe. And at time of di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner or ſupper, vſe more quantitie of meate then any other ſeaſon, and in meat vſe hot ſpicis, vvine &amp; muſtard, for theis make the body hoate, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the principall partes of the body, and concocte the could fleame ingendrid by this perilous and intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſeaſon of the yeare.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="regimen">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶A Regiment for ſpring tyme.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Pring tyme beginne the .xi. day of March and ende the .xii. of Iune. During vvhich tyme the blud in the body ſhalbe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid, and ingender Feuers, both ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians intermittent, and continuall, vvith Carbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cles, Botches, Dyſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, Squinancy, Infla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mations. etc. It ſhalbe very neceſſary therfore for all men (but eſpecially fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xvii. to .xl. yeres in age) to open a vaine, vomyt, or take purgation, vvhiche their myndes ſtande moſte vnto: othervvays they ſhalbe in maruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perill and daunger of death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ô dira caeli fata. Vſe exerciſe, but not ſo much as in the vvinter be not long faſting. Vſe thinges to make
<pb facs="tcp:20903:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the body looſe, alſo ſuche as be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vver, drye, and colde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="regimen">
            <head>¶A Regiment for the Sommer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ommer begin the xii. of Iune and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vntill the .xiii of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in vvhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſpace of time the body of man ſhalbe moleſtid greuouſly vvith red col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ingenderid of the intollerable heate, cauſing Phrenſie, Sinochus, and cauſon agues, vvhich ſhal gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly torment many young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, alſo morbos epidimiales, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilens, pthiſis, and other vvhiche I vvill not name. Therfore abſteine from vehement labor, vſe thinges that be cold, ſvveet, and pleaſaunt, and vvell ſmelling, of eaſy digeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:20903:6"/>
and eate litle meate. Yea to drinke cold vvater, vſing boyld meates al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>together, vvith bathing, vvaſhing and keping the bodye cleane from filthe both in the head, arme holes, feate, and hole body, and vſe al mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes vvhiche do coole and make the body moyſte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="regimen">
            <head>¶A Regiment for Autumne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vtumne begine the xiii. of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber and ende the .xii. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, and bycauſe the nature of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſhalbe inaequalis ac inordinata ac diuerſas infert paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones. Therfor chiefly in this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ther muſt be muche diligence vſid, for there can be no perfit or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der appointyd as is the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:20903:7"/>
becauſe that novve it ſhalbe hoat, novv cold, novv moyſt, novv drye, yea and in ſome daye al thies ſhal happen. ô quanta inclementia caeli. They that ſhall haue learning in phyſicke, novv let them haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſion on the miſeries that is lyke to fall by ſicknes. Notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is neceſſary to abſteine from exceſſe of meates and drinkes, ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keting, vvatching, laſciuious cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bering, vvhiche breede ravve and colde humors, and indigeſtid in the veines &amp; hoole body, abſtain, or at the leaſt, vſe moderate eating of the frutes of this ſeaſon as apples, pears plumbes, cheries, for they make ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cochymie and il iuyſe in the body, and vvyndines vvith colicke, and corrupte the meates if they be not eate firſt at meate. It is good in the beginning of this quarter to purge,
<pb facs="tcp:20903:7"/>
vomit, or let bloud, by thaduiſe of ſome learned Phyſition. Novve I vvill beginne briefly to touche the infirmities vvhiche ſhall reigne this yeare, beginning firſt vvith the contagius ſicknes of peſtilence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <head>¶Of the Peſtilence, vvith the cauſe vverof it ſpring, and the order in this diſeaſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny as vvell in times paſte as in oure late dayes, haue aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly vvryten of this dreadful and pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>relous ſicknes: I nede to ſpeake litle of it. Yet ſeing al men ether can not reade them, or els vnderſtand them, I thought it mete to ſet it forth for all mens health: in ſo muche as all
<pb facs="tcp:20903:8"/>
men ſhalbe in daunger of ſo cruell an enemy. And firſte, as touching the cauſe of it, there are diuers, one is the ſinnes and vvickednes of the people for vvhich God haue and do ſende the peſtilence for the revvard of ſynne. An other is taken of the ſterres and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtellation. Nam ortus &amp; occaſus ſyderum, magnae coniun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiones, luminum eclipſes, mutatio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes magnas in corporib. noſtris fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt. The laſt is taken of the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and phiſicians, vvhich is the inſpiration and dravving in of the peſtilentiall and corrupte aire, into the body ful of ravve humors, and ſuche as are apte to receiue cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. The next vvay to preſerue the body from this infirmitie is to open a vayne or purge, to flee from the corrupt aire, to vſe abſtinence, moderat diet, exerciſe, alſo fleeng
<pb facs="tcp:20903:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
long ſleepe, of often eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king vvhan as nature require it not this make the body preparid to the peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Alſo not to go abrode in the aire before the ſunne haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvid, &amp; vvha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you go abrode in the aire, eate ſome electuary, or other alexipharmacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faſtingas, Methrida<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum, treacle, bole armeniꝰ, and ſuch like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvering alſo ſome pomea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, vvell made to ſmell on, and not to eate meate and drinke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as ſom do, thinking therby to reſiſt the corrupt aire, but hovv ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly they do, I referre that to the iudgementes of ſuch as are ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd in phiſicke. The ſignes hovve to knovve if thou art infecte vvith this ſicknes, is not to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vrine, for that do often deceiue the moſt expt therin, but thou ſhalt fele thy ſelf ꝓne other vnto much ſlepe, or
<pb facs="tcp:20903:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
els that thou canſt eat in any caſe ſlepe vvith found imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s alſo pricking and tingling in the fleſhe, cold vvithout, but invvardly extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me hoat vvith drines, hedach, ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vomiting, and heauy cheare vvith out a manifeſt cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the cure of this ſicknes is to open a vayne if the age of the pacient, ſtrength, and time of the yeare agree hereto, nere to the place vvhere the ſvvelling apere (if ther be any) els in the part vvher he felith moſt grief, this ons being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this potio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to drinke. <hi>℞.</hi> Of the rootes of tormentill, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie, gentian, betony, ſet vval, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one .3. dragmes, of Bole arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, and terra ſigillata, eche tvvoo dragmes, of myrrhe and aloes hepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticke one ounce, of ſaffron halfe a dragme, beate theis &amp; make of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fine and ſubtil pouder, of vvhiche
<pb facs="tcp:20903:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
let the ſicke take in Scabies or Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentill vvater, halfe a dragme, and ſo being in bedde, he muſt be made to ſvveet .v. or .vi. houres accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſtrength of the pacient. And in all the time of his ſvveet, let him nether ſleepe, eate, nor drinke. After the ſvvet endyd, let him be dried vvith vvarme, and clene clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. And if he deſire to eate, giue him a litle broth made of a chickin, or ſuche like, but no great quantitie Let him keepe his chamber for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain daies after, and haue mery com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany, and muſicke, vſing perfumes in his chamber vvitth Maſticke, Myrrhe, Olibanꝰ, Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenſence. etc.</p>
            <p>If he haue any carbuncles, or ſores, becauſe the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians haue the dailie practiſe of it, I vvil omit it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:10"/>
            <head>¶Of the burning Feuer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Mytting all other kynde of Feuers, I vvill ſpeake of the cauſon or burnyng Feuer, becauſe there is as great feare of it this year, as euer vvas the laſt tvvo yeares paſt: as vvell in Englande, as in our clymate, by certaine and ſon dry conſtellations, in the Sommer ſeaſon. Therfore ſuche as are vexid vvith this burning feuer, before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinges let them be let bloud, yea ad animi ferè deliquiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Othervviſe the great heate vvill not be aſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid. Let them drinke ptiſanes, and could vvater, ſtrovving their cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers vvith vine leaues, bovves of vvillovve, colde herbes, and ſuche lyke. And giue them to drinke ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope
<pb facs="tcp:20903:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of Violets, Roſes, Nenuphar, yea and if you vvil, bathing ſhall be very profitable. So that all the cure of this diſeaſe, dooe conſiſt in theis tvvo pointes, that is, in expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the humor collerick abunding in the body, vvhiche is by lettinge bloud, vomyte, and ſvveating: and by extinguiſhing the great inflama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the liuer, vaines, arteries. etc. vvhiche is done by drinking colde vvater, ptiſanes, colde ſiropes, and Iulepes, before menſionid. This done being vvare of ſodain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the body, thou ſhalt by gods helpe come to thy perfit health.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:11"/>
            <head>¶Of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>F the enemies of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomy vvil main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tain their foliſh, and arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hir, this vvare ſufficient argument to ouerthrovve them, in that they do manifeſtly, ſe hovv the body of man is alterid, and troublid diuers vvayes, by the influence of the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly creatures (I meane the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and fixid ſterres,) as among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the quartaine is one, vvhoſe forſe I ſuppoſe, vvas not of longe time ſo generally knovven. Yea &amp; the heauens ſhall giue ſuche vnſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable vvether, that the humors rather ſhalbe more, and more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, to corruption: then to be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid to the health of the body, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:20903:11"/>
the quartaine ſhall not avvay at the ſpring (as many ſuppoſe) but driue vntyl Sommer, et vix tunc finietur. therfor in the ſpring it ſhalbe good to purge melancholicke, and phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick humors, yea and vnto ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g natures, to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a vaine. They muſt abſteyne from porke, biefe, ſalte meates, ravve frutes, goſe, ſvvanne, crane, ducke, and all foules liuinge in maryſhe placis. And vſe meates light of concoction, vvith good vvine vvhight and pleaſaunt, and finally all his diet muſt be, hovv to make his body, hoat and moyſt. And to flee thinges that are colde and drie, aſvvel out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vvardly as to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <pb facs="tcp:20903:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶Of the quotidian Ague.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y mynde is rather to preſcribe a good order of diet then a vvay of curation, in this and other agues vvhich do long mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſte the body, becauſe vvhere time do ſerue, there may be remedy and counſell ſought at the learned, but for their cauſe I vvrite, vvhiche dvvell farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maiſters of Phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſick in cuntrey tovvnes, and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The quotidian do inuade ſuch, as be groſſe, cold, and ſlugiſhe. And the fitte continevv from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thende .xviii. houres. The diet muſt be extenua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, et inciſoria. Vſing at the beginning, clyſters, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vvhan the diſeaſe doe more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, vſe Oximell, and thinges to
<pb facs="tcp:20903:12"/>
prouoke vrine: as the roote of ſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, perſely, fenell, flovverdeluce, and the .iiii. great ſeades vvhich are cold. &amp;c. Alſo in this caſe it is good to vomite, and anointe the ſtomack faſting, vvith the oyle of vvorme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvoode, maſtick, or petroleum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <head>¶Of dyſenteria or bloudy Flixe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Yſenterie in Greke, may be namid in Lattine tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina, but vvith vs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulceratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bovvels. Of this diſeaſe there be foure ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry kindes, as Galene vvriteth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but I vvrighting to the vnlearned, vvil omitte them, mynding rather to make them vnderſtande both it, and the remedies: then to make them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning in Galens doctrine, although ther is nothing more better, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb facs="tcp:20903:13"/>
nere in this caſe. The diſeaſe is manifeſt of it ſelfe for vvhan in the ſtole you perceiue yelovviſhe, or ſaffron color, oyliſhe, and fatte, or blody vvith fylmes (as it vvar per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chement vvete: they cal it excoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the guttes) vvith invvarde griping, pricking, and extreme pain ſo that they cum, ad animi deliquiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great heat, and maruelous drines. The vvaye to cure this ſicknes, is firſt to giue him mylke hoat from the covv, or els boilid, for to drink, if ſo be he haue no ague. (But if he haue an ague, then it vvill corrupte in the ſtomacke, and make his ague the more veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.) Alſo you may giue him to eate boylid tenderlye, colevvortes, alſo plantayne, ſorell, &amp;c. vvith the yolkes of egges. Let his drinke be rayne vvater but not ronning out of leaden ſpoutes: and
<pb facs="tcp:20903:13"/>
if you can not haue pure rayne vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and holſome, then take of foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne vvater of the rock, and dippe in it a gadde of ſtele red hoote, and let him drinke it: for it is meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly comfortable vnto the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the fluxe. Or if his ſtomack can not ſuffer vvater, you may giue him vvine vſid as you do the vvater aforeſaid. So that al the ſcope of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this malady is, per adſtringen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, reſicca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, vrina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mouentia. etc. medicines vvhiche in this caſe vve vſe, are thies. The rootes of roſeca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, holyoke, the leues of vvillovv revvpontick, ſanguis draconis, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſigillata, bolus armenius, mulbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, rayſine curnelles, the huſke of a pomegranate, the ſhels of ſea crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in pouder. etc. But if light thinges helpe not, then vvith all ſpede ſeke the helpe of the learnyd
<pb facs="tcp:20903:14"/>
maiſters, of phiſick. For I can not, nor any man, ſet forth all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer accidentes, that come in this ſickenes, they be ſo variable, and therfore cannot appointe any ſure, and perfit remedie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <head>¶Of the plureſy and the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lureſie, being Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus per peracutꝰ (and therfore moſte daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of any other before rehearſid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the peſtilence,) I thinke it mete, not litly to ouerpaſſe it, but alſo for thy vvelth ſumvvhat to make mention of it. This infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie ſpring of muche and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant bloud, flovvyng to the ribbes, and ther inflammed. The ſignes of it are ſhortnes of breath, a ſharpe,
<pb facs="tcp:20903:14"/>
and hard pulſe, a great pricking vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ribbes, vehement payne, vvith a continual ague: vvhiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at the firſt he feele not, yet in the proceſſe he ſhall (if the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the other, dooe not make it the more ſufferable.) He muſt for the firſt .iii. daies vſe only a ptiſane, aftervvarde milke of almondes, or fine bread vvith the broth of a cock, or in the end of the ſicknes, to drink vvater, in vvhich cinamome is boil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd. And alſo eate ſkaled fyſhes of cleane, and pure vvaters. The chefe practiſed remedy in this our time, is preſently to let bloud, on that parte the payne is. Nam natura ibi molitur euacuationem. The vaines in this caſe, is the lyuer vayne, or vayne of the ſplene called lienaria, if at the ſeuenth daye he feale great anguyſhe, and griefe, you muſt vſe
<pb facs="tcp:20903:15"/>
boxing vvith ſcarification, to ſucke ſanious bloud and matter. Alſo em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaſters made of dill, camomylle, roſecampine. &amp;c. boylid: not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting oyntmentes to rype the thing, vvith medicines to cauſe him voyde by ſpitting, the aforſaid cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Such is diadragacanthes, diapenideon, paſtilli pectorales, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cligma de pulmone vulpis, glicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhize, ſaccharum violatium, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>VVhiche diuers make mention of, in the cure of this diſeaſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disease">
            <head>¶Of the Revvmes and Catarrhus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Atarrhus cum vvha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the humour fall from the brayne, in to the mouthe, and iavves. This maye ſpryng of tvvo cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis:
<pb facs="tcp:20903:15"/>
ether by heat, diſſoling the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors conteinid in the head: or els by coldenes, of vvhich at this time I vvill touche the curatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfor it is very expedient, to auoyde all thinges vvhiche fill the head vvith vapours, as to muche drynking of vvyne, bathing, and vvaſhinge the head, vvith ſlepyng after meate, &amp; kembing the head alſo after meate, vvith great ſuppers, and late. Alſo onyons, garlycke, muſtard, radiſhe rotes: and al ravve herbes, and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, be augmenters of this miſchief. Therfor (abſtaining the thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentionid) it ſhalbe profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to anoynte the head vvith oyle of lylies, revve, dill, and almondes. Alſo you may by the aduiſe of ſom learnyd man, take ſome clyſter, or other potion, vvhiche do expel the hurtfull humor. You may moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb facs="tcp:20903:16"/>
make a tvvilte, and applie it to your head, vvith theis thinges fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lovving, made in pouder <hi>℞.</hi> of the floures of betony, melilote,, and ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>momyll, the leaues of roſes dried, laurel, penereal, and orage, of euery one halfe an handful, of cinamome, and cloues, one dragme: of nutmegs a dragme, and an halfe: of macis half a dragme: bring all thies in to pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and make of them a tvvilte, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to vſe and art. It is alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good to purge the head by ſternu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation, and neſing, vvith the iuſe of of beetes, or colevvortes, loking to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vvard the ſonne, or ſuch like thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> moreouer it is very ꝓfitable to dry the brayne, vvith odoriferous bals, and pomeambres: and alſo vvith fumes made on the coles, holding his head ouer it faſting in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. You may in this caſe, vſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick,
<pb facs="tcp:20903:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lignum aloes, gallamoſcata, frankenſence, baye beries, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, muſke, roſemary, cloues, cinamome, &amp;c. vvhich be very medicinable in this behalfe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <date>ANNO CHRISTI. 1559. Menſe Martij.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
